Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today is we are Daf Nun
Gimmel דף נג, Daf Nun Gimmel, it is the what day is
it, the tenth day in the Omer עומר, Omer, the ninth day,
tenth. Good to know somebody is counting. Okay, I cannot remember from
the night before. Tenth day in the Omer עומר. Omer. We pick
up with the Mishna משנה, Mishna, which is one we get today,
we pick up on the Mishna משנה Mishna on Daf Nun Bet
Amud Bet דף נב עמוד ב, Daf Nun Bet Amud Bet, and
this is going to be a really fun Mishna משנה, Mishna, so
let us get started. Hamikadesh Bechelko bein Kodshei Kodashim bein Kodashim Kalim
המקדש בחלקו בין קדשי קדשים בין קדשים קלים, Hamikadesh Bechelko bein Kodshei
Kodashim bein Kodashim Kalim, a somebody marries a woman, and now we
are talking about the objects used to do Kiddushin קידושין Kiddushin and
whether they are considered to have a Shaveh Perutah שוה פרוטה Shaveh
Perutah or not, just a Shaveh Perutah שוה פרוטה Shaveh Perutah in
the simple sense of the market value, but questions about the nature
of
ownership and the Halachic status of the object. So a Kohen כהן
Kohen marries a woman, well it could be a Yisrael ישראל Yisrael
we will see in a minute, but somebody marries a woman whether
with his portion in the Kodshei Kodashim קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, so
this would be talking specifically about a Kohen כהן. Kohen. A Kohen
כהן Kohen eats from the Chatas חטאת, Chatas, right, the sin offering
which is or expiation offering which could always is the meat of
it is eaten by the Kohen כהן, Kohen, only by the Kohen
כהן, Kohen, only
male Kohanim כהנים Kohanim and only in the Azarah עזרה, Azarah, the
immediate sort of temple precincts, right, just to remind everybody someone better
be drawing a picture of the Azarah עזרה Azarah than about brother-in-laws.
Okay, so
anyway,
what I would think it be Me'ilah מעילה, Me'ilah, being
Me'ilah מעילה Me'ilah in the thing, right,
he is using it for some transactional purpose.
Anyway, okay, alright, anyway,
here is here is the Mizbe'ach מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Okay, start, anyway, that
is the this is right, this is the Kodesh Kodashim קדש קדשים,
Kodesh Kodashim, right, this is the Kodesh קדש Kodesh or the Heichal
היכל. Heichal. Okay, anyway, actually then you had an Ulam אולם Ulam
here, alright, then you had the Mizbe'ach מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Okay, and then
you had here this was Ezras Yisrael עזרת ישראל, Ezras Yisrael,
this was called Ezras Kohanim עזרת כהנים, Ezras Kohanim, or just the
whole thing is just all this whole thing is the Azarah עזרה.
Azarah. Okay, and then maybe I drew this too big, I probably
did draw this too big, sorry about that, let us start again.
Ulam אולם, Ulam,
Heichal היכל. Heichal.
Okay, so then you have
this is the Azarah עזרה, Azarah, okay, and that is Ezras Yisrael
עזרת ישראל, Ezras Yisrael, and then you have here the Ezras Nashim
עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, you
will see why that is all very relevant in a minute. Anyway,
okay, so the Kodshei Kodashim קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim can only be
eaten, the Chatas חטאת Chatas can only be eaten by male Kohanim
כהנים Kohanim and only in the Azarah עזרה. Azarah. That area, I
need another color, but this area here is the Azarah עזרה. Azarah.
Stay in the Azarah עזרה Azarah for that purpose, like put a
picnic table,
yeah, I do not know, they were not allowed to sit so
they had to eat standing,
right, basically yes.
Okay, anyway, so that so Chevre חברה, Chevre, so somebody a male
Kohen כהן Kohen who has a portion in the Chatas חטאת Chatas
goes ahead to a woman and says I am marrying you with
this steak of the Chatas חטאת, Chatas, that is his portion in
the Kodshei Kodashim קדשי קדשים. Kodshei Kodashim. Kodashim Kalim קדשים קלים Kodashim
Kalim can be a Kohen כהן Kohen or Yisrael ישראל, Yisrael, a
male or a female, it is the meat of a Shlamim שלמים,
Shlamim, can be eaten in all Yerushalayim ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So somebody brings
a Shlamim שלמים, Shlamim, he is bringing this meat home barbecue for
somewhere in his house there in the Jewish quarter and he goes
to a woman and he says I am marrying you with this
hamburger. Okay, Eina Mekudeshes אינה מקודשת, Eina Mekudeshes, she is not married.
Alright, because we will see even though he has the right to
eat that meat, the short version is, the language of the Gemara
גמרא Gemara is Mishulchan Gavoa Ka Zachu משלחן גבוה קא זכו, Mishulchan
Gavoa Ka Zachu, he is eating off of God's table. It is
not his meat, he has a right to be eating God's meat,
the meat that came from the Mizbe'ach מזבח, Mizbe'ach, not literally from
the Mizbe'ach מזבח Mizbe'ach but figuratively. Okay, so he cannot marry a
woman with that meat. The Maaser Sheni מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, now
let us it is Maaser Sheni מעשר שני Maaser Sheni which you
have to bring up and eat in Yerushalayim ירושלים, Yerushalayim, bein shogeg
bein mezid בין שוגג בין מזיד, bein shogeg bein mezid, whether it
was knowingly or unknowingly, whether he knew it was Maaser Sheni מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni money or she knew it was or Maaser Sheni
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni fruit, lo kidesh לא קידש, lo kidesh, he
had not married her.
A Yisrael ישראל, Yisrael, right, any
back and right, the same thing the beginning could also be Yisrael
ישראל Yisrael if it was Kodashim Kalim קדשים קלים. Kodashim Kalim. Okay,
he marries a woman with Maaser Sheni מעשר שני Maaser Sheni fruit,
whether knowingly or unknowingly that that is the fruit, it is not
a good Kiddushin קידושין, Kiddushin, Divrei Rabbi Meir דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei
Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Yehuda omer beshogeg lo kidesh bemezid kidesh רבי יהודה
אומר בשוגג לא קידש במזיד קידש, Rabbi Yehuda omer beshogeg lo kidesh
bemezid kidesh, if it was unintentional it did not work, intentional it
did, we will see about all of that in the Gemara גמרא,
Gemara, yeah we will see about now Behekdesh בהקדש, Behekdesh, now let
us say it was Hekdesh הקדש Hekdesh money, okay he had sanctified
his TV for donating it to the Beis HaMikdash בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, okay and he had forgotten about that and then he married
the woman with the TV. Okay, so when some object that belonged
to הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*. במזיד bemezed, קידש *be-mezid kidesh*, if it was
knowing, if he remembered that it was הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, ובשוגג *u-veshogeg*
lo it works. בשוגג beshogeg לא קידש lo kideish. *bishogeg lo kidesh*,
it was unintentional, it did not, דברי רבי מאיר Rebi Meir *divrei
Rabbi Meir*. So that actually, you know, it's interesting again, we have
here the reverse possibility of whether of שוגג shogeg ומזיד *shogeg u-mezid*...
because remember רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* by the מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni *Maaser Sheni*, he said that מזיד mezid *mezid* works better.
And here, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, wait, this is the same thing.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* said by the מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni. *Maaser Sheni* that, wait wait, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
said by the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, *Maaser Sheni*
that מזיד meizid *mezid* worked better. הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, it's, it's also
same point. But this time according to רבי מאיר Rebi Meir *Rabbi
Meir*. מזיד meizid *mezid* works, שוגג shogeg *shogeg* does not work. רבי
יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda Omer, בשוגג beshogeg קידש מזיד meizid לא קידש
lo kideish *Rabbi Yehuda omer beshogeg kidesh mezid lo kidesh*, the exact
mirror image. שוגג shogeg, *shogeg* works, מזיד mezed? *mezid* does not. So
a lot of things we're going to have to unpack there about
שוגג shogeg. ומזיד *shogeg u-mezid* by מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, *Maaser Sheni*
and by הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, but we're going to start by the
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *Kodshei Kodashim* and קדשים קלים kodashim kalim, *Kodashim
Kalim*.
Yes. They're talking about מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni *Maaser Sheni* brought about
מעשר maaser כסף *Maaser Keseph*.
I know you, that's always your pet thing, but that's not what
we're talking about right now. Yes.
There's a change in the language from מקודשת mekudeshes. *mekudeshet* to קידש
*kidesh*. We've seen that before.
In other words, where does the רישא *Reisha* say מקודשת mekudeshes. *mekudeshet*?
Oh right, I see. המקדש *ha-mekadesh*, that's an interesting language. Yeah yeah,
oh it's an interesting, that's a good question. I don't know why.
Okay, so נימא מתניתין דלא כרבי יוסי הגלילי *neima matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi
Yosi HaGelili*, let's hear a משנה mishna *Mishnah* is not like רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili. *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili*, this issue that קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim *Kodashim Kalim* is not considered the owned by the
person who has the right to eat it, the person who brought
the קרבן korban, *korban*, and he can't marry a woman. Let's say
it's not like רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili. *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili*.
דתניא detanya, *de-tanya* we learned in the ברייתא braita *Baraita*: ומעלה מעל
בהשם *u-ma'ala ma'al b'Hashem*.
Okay, this is actually not talking what you would think about מעילה
me'ila *me-ilah* by קדשים kodashim. *kodshim*, but it's talking about somebody who
swears falsely that he does not own have in his possession something
that belongs to his neighbor. Somebody says I gave you this for
safe keeping, he says no you didn't, he says swear to me,
he swears, he's lying, that is a trespass against God because he's
using God's name to perpetrate a sin and to take possession and
to hold onto something that isn't his, and he has to bring
a קרבן korban? *korban*. Okay, that's the context here. Not מעילה me'ila
*me-ilah*, but a trespass against God using God's name to swear falsely
about something that should be in his possession. But because it uses
the word בהשם *b'Hashem*, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili *Rabbi Yosi
HaGelili* teaches the following thing: ומעלה מעל בהשם לרבות קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim שהם ממונו דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili, *u-ma'ala ma'al
b'Hashem le-rabot Kodashim Kalim she-hem mamono divrei Rabbi Yosi HaGelili*. That basically
if Michael goes ahead and gives me his שלמים shlamim *shlamim* and
says Dov, here, hold onto my sheep here, I'm going to go
bring it as a שלמים shlamim, *shlamim* next week, I need you
to watch it for me while I go on a vacation, you
know, feed it, take care of it, okay? Then he comes back
from his vacation and he says where's my שלמים shlamim *shlamim* sheep?
I've got to now bring it to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*, I've already sanctified it. I say yeah, what what are
you talking about? What sheep? So he says swear to me and
I swear to him. Am I חייב chayav, *chayav* now for having
taken an oath to use it to steal his money, or do
we say that wasn't your money? That was a קרבן korban? *korban*,
I mean, not like what I did was acceptable, but that's not
this פרשה *parsha* of swearing as a way of taking your money,
because it wasn't yours once it was a קרבן korban, *korban*. So
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili. *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili* says because it
uses the word בהשם *b'Hashem*, we're talking even about sanctified objects. Now,
he doesn't say all sanctified objects, he says we'll identify it as
קדשים קלים kodashim kalim. *Kodashim Kalim*. קדשים קלים kodashim kalim, *Kodashim Kalim*
of all sanctified objects is the one that most belongs to the
owner. If Michael had sanctified his car as a donation to the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, he has no rights left to
the car. He just delivers it to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*, they come pick it up, cars for הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*.
Okay, so they come pick it up, he's gone. So he no
longer owns it, it's owned by the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. If
he sanctified his sheep as an עולה *olah*, as a קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim *Kodshei Kodashim*, or as a חטאת chatas. *chatat*, he's not
going to get anything out of it. It's all going to go
on the מזבח mizbei'ach, *mizbe-ach* or the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim* are going
to eat it. So that's not his. But if it's קדשים קלים
Kodashim Kalim *Kodashim Kalim*, he's going to be able to eat the
meat in all of ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*. So maybe it's still his
animal, his animal that he's going to bring as a קרבן korban,
*korban*, but it's still his. So that's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGelili, *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili* says. This פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* tells me
that there's some הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* that still is considered yours, and
that's קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim *Kodashim Kalim*. And this is in general
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili, *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili*'s position, that קדשים
קלים ממון בעלים kodashim kalim mamon be-alim, הם *Kodashim Kalim mamon ba-alim
hem*, it's considered to be still belong to the owner. If I
damage the animal, do I have to pay you? If it's your
sheep that you sanctified as a שלמים shlamim *shlamim*? רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose Ha-Glili *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili* would say yes. Okay, so according
to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili*, I should be
able to marry a woman with the steaks from my קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim, *Kodashim Kalim*, because it's mine, right? So makes a lot
of sense.
Why can the גמרא gemara *Gemara* say למעט קדשים קלים kodashim kalim
*lema-et Kodashim Kalim*, why לרבות *lerabot*? Even קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
*Kodashim Kalim* are included in the קרבן korban *korban* I bring for
swearing falsely as a way of stealing your money.
Exactly. So the point here is when I steal your money with
a false oath, stealing your money included in stealing your money is
stealing your קדשים קלים kodshim kalim *Kodashim Kalim*. דברי רבי יוסי Rebi
Yosi הגלילי שהן ממונו *divrei Rabbi Yosi HaGelili she-hein mamono*. So our
משנה mishna seems to be not רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi הגלילי. So
גמרא gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבי יוסי הגלילי. afilu teima Rabbi
Yose HaGelili. It could even be רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi הגלילי. כי
קאמר רבי יוסי הגלילי מחייב. ki ka'amar Rabbi Yose HaGelili mechayev. When
does רבי יוסי הגלילי say that this שלמים shlamim? sheep is yours
and if I swear use an oath to steal it essentially I
have to pay, you know, I'm חייב, that's when it's still alive.
אבל לאחר שחיטה לא. aval le'achar shechita lo. Once it's been shechted,
then it's no longer yours, which is interesting. You would think אדרבא,
aderaba, now that it's shechted, now I'm eating the meat, now it's
all the more so mine, I'm benefiting from it. But the גמרא
Gemara says מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? And here even according to
רבי יוסי הגלילי, כי קא זכו משולחן גבוה קא זכו. ki ka
zachu mishulchan gavo'ah ka zachu. Once it's been brought as a קרבן,
korban you are now eating it off of God's table. Everybody, even
the בעלים, be'alim, even קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim even קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim, according to רבי יוסי הגלילי. The אימורים imurim get put, the
דם dam gets put on the מזבח, mizbei'ach. the אימורים imurim get
burnt up, and now God is giving you a portion at the
רבי'ס Rebbe's טיש. tish. It's God's טיש. tish. You're getting a portion
off of that table. You're not eating your meat, you're eating the
meat that's coming from the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Okay, which is interesting, which
then raises the question, then why is it considered mine before I
brought it as a קרבן?
korban But you know, דוחקא, dochka, it's not eating off God's table.
I know, but what right do I have with it? What ownership
do I have with it before it's being brought? וצריך עיון, v'tzarich
iyun, right? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, it says?
No, it's a
bit anyway, it's a little bit of a question because eventually I'm
going to get to keep a piece of it that makes it
I don't know, it's a little bit funny because you would think
that your control and benefit and rights to it is even less
before it's been brought. But nevertheless, that's what we're saying. For רבי
יוסי הגלילי, it's considered your animal before it's been brought. Once it's
been brought, then you've given it to God. That's when you actually
have given it to God, and now you're getting something back from
God. And therefore, it's not yours once it's meat. Okay. דיקא נמי
דקתני המקדש בחלקו בין קדשי קדשים בין קדשים קלים. deika nami diktani
hamekadish bechelko bein kodshei kodashim bein kodashim kalim. The משנה mishna seems
to, you know, it can be a clear, a precise reading of
the משנה mishna shows you that because it says your portion, meaning
it's not the whole animal, it's the piece of the animal you
get. So we're talking about after it's been offered on the
מזבח. mizbei'ach, So לא קידש. lo kideish, שמע מינה. shma mina. So
that is a good proof. You see that we are talking about,
you see we're talking about after the animal's been offered, not giving
the whole animal. So according to רבי יוסי הגלילי, if I took
this sheep which was קדשים קלים kodashim kalim, and it was still
alive sheep and I gave it to a woman and said הרי
את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, maybe it would work. Although
I don't exactly understand how because what good does it do for
her? But anyway. But once it's my portion in it, it's been
offered, given to God, and I'm now just getting my portion off
of the מזבח, I'm getting my meat, the rest has been God's
portion, that's not mine anymore. That's I'm eating from God's altar, from
God's table, and I can't and it's not my money and I
can't marry a woman with it.
Yeah. לא קידש lo kideish. versus אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet.
No, our משנה mishna says לא קידש, lo kideish, originally when it
quoted the משנה mishna לא קידש. lo kideish. Right.
Oh, that's a good point. Michael just makes a good point. This
quote of the משנה mishna has לא קידש, not אינה מקודשת. eina
mekudeshet. We'll have to check the different גרסאות. girsa'ot. Yes.
But if it's שלמים, shlamim, she could then take that שלמים shlamim,
sheep to the בית המקדש and enjoy it herself.
Yeah, it's an interesting question about being מקריב makriv a שלמים that
somebody else was מקדיש makdish in their name and how that exactly
works. So anyway. All right, let's take a look. Now we get
an interesting story. Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught. Okay.
But that's the basic principle of the first part of the משנה
Mishnah? about using the חלק cheilek in the קרבנות, korbanot, which is
that even if it's the רבי יוסי who says you have the
most sense of ownership, once it's the meat you're getting after it's
been offered, you've given it to God, it's no longer yours.
Has anyone ever tried doing this?
Yeah, but that's not yet, but we're not going there. תנו רבנן.
tanu rabanan. לאחר פטירתו של רבי מאיר.
le'achar petirato shel Rabbi
Meir. Now remember, the משנה Mishnah was taught סתם stam about קדשי
קדשים Kodshei Kodashim and קדשים kodashim קלים. Now we're going to see
and סתם משנה רבי מאיר. stam mishna Rabbi Meir. Now we're going
to see it actually was not always agreed upon. תנו רבנן. tanu
rabanan. לאחר פטירתו של רבי מאיר, le'achar petirato shel Rabbi Meir, after
Rabbi Meir died, אמר להם רבי יהודה לתלמידיו, amar lahem Rabbi Yehuda
l'talmidav, Rabbi Yehuda said to his students, אל יכנסו תלמידי רבי מאיר
לכאן. al yikansu talmidei Rabbi Meir l'chan. Don't let Rabbi Meir's students
come into our בית מדרש. beit midrash. מפני שקנתרנין הן, mipnei shekantarnin
hen, because they're troublemakers, ולא ללמוד תורה הן באין, v'lo lilmod Torah
hen ba'in, they're not sincerely coming to learn תורה, Torah, אלא לקפחני
בהלכות הן באין. ela lekofachni behalachot hen ba'in. They're coming to show
off how smart they are. They want to challenge me with their
knowledge and so on and it's all a mind game for them,
they're not sincerely coming to learn. So don't let them come in,
they're disruptive, they're troublemakers. Okay. דחק סומכוס, dachak Sumchus, so סומכוס, Sumchus,
one of Rabbi Meir's תלמידים מובהקים, talmidim muvhakim, forced his way in
ונכנס, venichnas, and entered the בית מדרש. beit midrash. אמר להם, amar
lahem, and then he got up and he said, כך שנה לי
רבי מאיר, kach shana li Rabbi Meir, here's what Rabbi Meir taught
to me: המקדש בחלקו בין קדשי קדשים בין קדשים קלים, hamekadish bechelko
bein kodshei kodashim bein kodashim kalim, oh here again, לא קידש. So
exactly, not אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. Once again. So if somebody marries
a woman with his portion in קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim or קדשים
kodashim. קלים, it does not work. Okay, so that seems a reasonable
thing to be talking about. כעס רבי יהודה עליהם. ka'as Rabbi Yehuda
aleihem. Rabbi Yehuda got angry on his students. אמר להם, amar lahem,
לא כך אמרתי לכם, lo kach amarti lachem, didn't I tell
you? to show off, to
challenge me, to challenge me.
How this whole thing is such an absurd case because how would
a woman ever be in the עזרה? Azara? Okay now why? Because
קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim. can't be out of the עזרה. Azara. קדשים
קלים to be all in ירושלים, Yerushalayim but remember, here's my עזרת
נשים, Ezras Nashim, that's why I drew this, to show you the
presumption that women are always out of the עזרה. Azara. The עזרה
Azara starts with עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisrael and the קדשי קדשים Kodshei
Kodashim, can't go out of the עזרה. Azara. So he says look,
this is all a mind game, this is not like they really
want to know הלכה. halacha. You might, you could appreciate this. We're
not interested in discussing theoretical issues. It's absurd, right? It shows you're
not really sincerely coming to understand because there's no הלכה למעשה halacha
l'ma'aseh about this. A woman would never get be in the עזרה
Azara to eat the so that she could receive the קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim So this is all just them like like just doing
it to prove how smart they are. It's not because they really
want to know the הלכה למעשה halacha l'ma'aseh because this isn't הלכה
למעשה. halacha l'ma'aseh.
But what about the קדשים קלים problem?
Okay, but he wanted to know why you're teaching קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim. which is interesting because you know really like he assumes that
every discussion in the גמרא Gemara has to have to be like
למעשה. l'ma'aseh. He can't deal with a hypothetical? But maybe but it
wasn't just hypothetical, it was impossible. So why are we talking about
it? What about a שליח? shaliach? Ah, so let's see what the
answer is. So
אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rebi Yosi, רבי יוסי said, יאמרו מאיר שח,
Yomru Meir shach, people who say מאיר Meir died, יהודה כעס, Yehuda
ka'as, יהודה Yehuda got angry at רב מאיר's Reb Meir students which
was actually in the front to רב מאיר's Reb Meir whole approach
to learning. It wasn't about שמחה, simcha, it was about רב מאיר
Reb Meir and his students, right? And his whole approach. So יוסי
שתיק Yosi shatik and if I'm silent תפי תורה מה תהא עליה?
Tifei Torah mah tehei aleiha? What's going to be with the honor
of תורה? Torah? Right? We're going to let the you know and
I'm going to be complicit in this defaming of רבי מאיר Rebi
Meir. and his whole approach. I mean if I have an answer
I can give.
We're not just an answer if I tolerate this idea of this
sentence of this challenge that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir, whole his students
and his approach and so on. So now I'm going to respond
to defend רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Number one,
וכי אין אדם מסור לקבל קידושין לבתו בעזרה? V'chi ein adam masur
lekabel kiddushin l'vito b'Azara? Maybe this guy's marrying off his daughter, his
under-age daughter? So that's how you don't need a woman in the
עזרה. Azara. A man is there marrying off his under-age daughter. Number
one. Number two, ואין אשה עשויה לעשות לה שליח לקבל קידושיה בעזרה?
V'ein isha asuya la'asos lah shaliach lekabel kiddusheha b'Azara?
Since when can a woman not make a man to be her
שליח shaliach and she can represent her and he can I know
alright and number three, ועוד דחקה ונכנסה מה היא? v'od dachaka v'nichnasa
mah hi?
And let's say she forced her way in then what would be
the הלכה? halacha? Obviously playing off on the beginning where he forced
his way into the בית מדרש. Beis Midrash. Okay so obviously it's
worth discussing it's not that it's impossible for this to take place.
Now a very nice little story, it's a lot of fun, interestingly
this becomes relevant for discussions about מחיצה. mechitzah. Why? Because for some
people the idea of a מחיצה mechitzah in שול shul is based
on the idea in the בית המקדש that you would have an
עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim separate from the עזרת ישראל. Ezras Yisrael. And
this גמרא Gemara seems to indicate that, that a woman had no
place being in the עזרה, Azara, so that the עזרה Azara was
completely male space. Which obviously raises you know is like I think
at a certain like theological level challenging. It means like really like
the basic עזרה, Azara, the בית המקדש was women were not allowed
there? The basic place of worship was only a was exclusively a
male place? It sounds like that אשה בעזרה מניין. Isha b'Azara minayin.
So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says five lines
right five lines before the lines get wide, וכי אשה בעזרה מניין,
V'chi isha b'Azara minayin, רש"י Rashi says דקתני קדשי קדשים והרי הן
אין יוצאים חוץ לעזרה אפילו לעזרת נשים הן נפסלים ביוצא והנשים אינן
נכנסות לה. D'katani Kodshei Kodashim v'harei hen ein yotzim chutz l'Azara afilu
l'Ezras Nashim hen nifsalim b'yotzei v'hanashim einan nichnasos lah. Women can't go
into the עזרה Azara כדיתנן באבות הטומאה פרק קמא דכלים, Keditnan b'Avos
HaTumah perek kama d'Keilim, like it teaches in the first paragraph of
כלים. Keilim. You look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says, פירש בקונטרס
דאין אשה נכנסת בעזרה כדיתנן פרק קמא דכלים, Peirash bakuntres d'ein isha
nichneses b'Azara keditnan perek kama d'Keilim, ולא דק, V'lo dak, רש"י Rashi
was not being careful, דלא אשכחן בשום דוכתא דנשים אסורות ליכנס בעזרה.
D'lo ashkechan b'shum דוכתא douchta d'nashim asuros likanes b'Azara. Nowhere does it
say that a woman cannot enter the עזרה. Azara. And then he
discusses the משניות mishnayos that רש"י Rashi was referring to and he
says the משניות mishnayos clearly are not excluding women. And then if
you skip to the bottom third of תוספות Tosafos right by the
parenthesis he says, ועוד תנן פרק כל הפסולים ששחיטה כשרה בנשים, V'od
tnan perek Kol HaPsulim she'shechitah keshira b'nashim, that a woman could be
a שוחט shochet for קדשים. אם כן היא יכולה ליכנס בעזרה, Im
ken hi yechola likanes b'Azara, how can you שחט shecht the קדשים
without being in the עזרה? Azara? So maybe have a long knife
or something anyway. ועוד הרי סוטה ונזירה נכנסות בעזרה להניף, V'od harei
Sotah u'Nezira nichnasos b'Azara l'hanif, women have to go when they're bringing
their קרבנות korbanos and they can't send a representative they have to
do the תנופה. tenufah. לכך נראה לי דאשה בעזרה להתקדש מניין. L'kach
nireh li d'isha b'Azara l'hiskadesh minayin. What's a woman doing in the
עזרה Azara to get married? You know I mean they talk about
renting a nice hall for the wedding but still. Okay so הרי
אין רגילות שתכנס לשם כדי להתקדש שהרי
בזיון הוא. Harei ein regilus shetikanes l'sham k'dei l'hiskadesh sheharei bizayon hu.
מילתא דלא שכיחא. Milsa d'lo sh'chicha. Now of course it's not just
that it's absurd to do a קידושין kiddushin in the עזרה Azara
altogether. because presumably that question was answered when you said that her
father was doing it for her or a man was doing it
for her, but somehow it's the combination of the two. Still fundamentally
there is an עזרת נשים, Ezras Noshim, right? So still that's even
according to I mean yes, תוספות Tosafos is right and all the
ראשונים rishonim פוסקים poskim agree that women do go into the עזרה
Azora when they're bringing קרבנות korbanot and so on, but there's still
is this presumption that there needs to be some like it can't
be for a trivial purpose. You know, so the combination of the
fact that it's a woman and for this purpose of getting married,
which is not an appropriate normally an appropriate thing to be doing
in the עזרה, Azora, that's the question. ומשום דלא שכיחא ולא איירי
תנא מינה. u-mishum de-lo sh'chicha ve-lo ayri tana minah. Why would we
be talking about such an absurd case? So somehow, just getting married,
that would be okay. Just a woman in the עזרה, Azora, that
would be okay. But a woman to be in the עזרה Azora
for the purpose of getting married, the combination of that too. Anyway,
it is very relevant for this discussion of using this as a
model for a what do you call it, for מחיצה. mechitza. Do
we actually conceptualize that the basic מקום עבודה, makom avoda, מקום המקדש,
makom hamikdash, worship space, was exclusively male? Right? That women were not
allowed there? I mean, I guess the alternative is predominantly male, but
still there's a difference between that and exclusively male. For example, Rav
Moshe Feinstein dealt with the question about a woman entering when there's
not a shul that basically women don't go to at all and
there's no מחיצה, mechitza,
you know, because it's all men, and a woman comes, you know,
to can a woman come, you know, ad hoc to say קדיש
Kaddish and stand in the back? So Rav Moshe basically says yes,
and he says that's what the that in ליטא, Lita, he said
that they would that you know when a woman would come in
either like to collect either to collect צדקה tzedaka or to say
קדיש Kaddish and there wouldn't be a מחיצה, mechitza, she would just
stand in the back and that would be okay. So first of
all, it's interesting because in passing, I don't think the question was
about קדיש, Kaddish, but I forget what the question was about, but
in passing he mentioned that in ליטא Lita women would say come
to the שול shul and say קדיש. Kaddish. But besides which, it's
like it's, you know, if fundamentally it's not a mixed space, if
fundamentally it's a male space, then it doesn't mean that a woman
can't enter in like in an ad hoc type of a basis.
Now, he didn't want to have her sitting in the middle of
all the men, you know, sitting like apart from the men. But
anyway, it is interesting thinking about this as a model. And even
within תוספות's Tosafos approach, there's a discussion how much is it like,
you know, is it that women need a justifiable reason to enter
into the עזרה, Azora, meaning like they need to be bringing a
קרבן? korban. And if they're not bringing a קרבן, korban. they can't
enter at all. Let's say they just want to come in to
see the כהנים, Kohanim, their husband's bringing a קרבן, korban I don't
know, their friend's bringing whatever, they you know do they need to
have only when they're bringing a קרבן korban. or is it only
when it's like completely trivial and inappropriate like the קידושין Kiddushin they
shouldn't be coming in? You know, what type of justification is needed?
But anyway, very, you know, interesting and I think in certain levels
theologically challenging around this issue. Yes, the עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisroel
was not included as part of the עזרה? Azora?
It is included. Oh, okay, so it's a
bit yeah, sorry.
Yeah. Okay, no problem. Yeah. And then because if a woman and
they also pointed out the opinion that נשים סומכות רשות, noshim somchos
reshus, they also do סמיכה smicha over there, right?
Yeah, but but then but if you remember that case says הביאוה
לעזרת נשים וסמכו עליה, hevi'uha le-Ezras Noshim ve-somchu aleha,
that we had a קרבן korban that we brought to the עזרת
נשים Ezras Noshim and we had the women do סמיכה smicha in
the עזרת נשים. Ezras Noshim. Yes, Charlie.
Now that he's mentioned that according to מסכת מדות, Masechet Middos, which
maybe it wasn't studied anywhere as it is today, there was actually
a separate women's entrance to the עזרה. Azora. So if women were
never...
I think it was on the north side.
No,
in this עזרה? Azora? You sure? You sure you're not talking about
the...
no, no, there was a... it's in מסכת מדות. Masechet Middos.
All right, you show me. I'm not remembering that either. Okay, anyway,
no, I think or maybe it was for יולדות yoldos that they
brought their קרבן korban and they'd have a particular exit after they
brought their קרבן. korban You might be right.
I think it was for them to bring their קרבן.
korban You might be right, but yes, yes, but that's for a
יולדת yoledes who is bringing her קרבן korban. if I remember correctly.
Okay, one last point and then we'll move on, which is about
a woman making a שליח shliach so you can make sure there's
all men there. It just reminded me, I think I might have
told you this before, anyway, I was once at this wedding
which was a very, very פרום frum wedding, I don't know if
you've been to weddings like this where like, you know, the entrances
like the card even the card like the card tables are separate
for the men and the women, the entrances are separate, like you
know you never see each other in person. Anyway, I was there
so I was with like a couple of people that have a
sense of humor, so one of them was David Schatz and when
we were sort of there at the שמורג shmorg he was saying
to me, you know, this wedding is so פרום, frum, I don't
know if I'm allowed to have mixed feelings.
And then when it came time for the חופה, chuppah, so the
חופה, chuppah, it was like everybody who walked down the aisle was
except for the כלה, kallah, right, was a man, like you know
this big hat, you know, and the whole
getup, right, the black suit or whatever. So there was this like
poor little כלה kallah amongst like these twenty guys, you know, in
their black hats and black suits. So somebody else sitting next to
me said, you know, they're not really being פרום frum enough. If
they really wanted to be פרום, frum, she would just have made
her brother her שליח. shliach. and we would
have had all men up there. So anyway. All right, so there
you go. She can make a שליח. shaliach. All right, moving on.
The ברייתא braita, says like this.
Okay, תניא, Tanya, we taught a ברייתא, braita. bottom of
נ"ב עמוד ב'. Nun-Beis Amud Beis. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר, מקודשת.
mekudeshet. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi Omer, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was not only obsessed, first he was obsessed
about the whole discussion, but if he's going to enter into the
discussion, we still have the same רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
יוסי positions, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda argues on רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, he's consistent fighting against this position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir,
A, we're discussing it, B, you're wrong, she is מקודשת. רבי יוסי
siding with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, שניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. shneihem mikra echad darshu.
They're both learning from
one פסוק. pasuk וזה יהיה לך מקדש הקדשים מן האש. Vezeh yiheyeh
lecha mikodesh hakodashim min ha'esh. This shall be your portion, the כהנים,
Kohanim from the holy of holies, and it's the meat of the
חטאת. רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi Yehuda savar, לך, lecha, ולכל צרכיך. ul'chol
tzorchecha. This is yours. You can use it for whatever you want.
Obviously, only a כהן, Kohen, male כהן Kohen can eat it in
the עזרה. Azarah. But if you are able to find some other
use for it once you get it and eventually it's going to
be eaten, you can sell it to your fellow male כהן, Kohen,
you can use it to marry a woman, whatever latitude you have
within only male כהנים Kohanim? eating it in the עזרה, Azarah, you
can make use of it. רבי יוסי סבר, Rabbi Yossi savar, כאש.
ke'esh. No,
it's like the fire. מה אש לאכילה אף כאן נמי לאכילה. Mah
esh l'achilah af kan nami l'achilah. Interesting, he doesn't say fire you
don't have any control over, but it says, fire is there to
consume, this also is to be consumed, and you don't really have
any ownership over it, it's just to be consumed.
שולחן גבוה. shulchan gavo'ah. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Yochanan
said, top of
נ"ג עמוד א', Nun-Gimmel Amud Aleph, נמנו וגמרו. nimnu v'gamru. They took
a vote and they came to the
conclusion המקדש בחלקו בין קדשי קדשים בין קדשים קלים לא קידש. hamikadesh
bechelko bein kodshei kodashim bein kodashim kalim lo kadesh. That if somebody
marries a woman whether it's קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim. and even קדשים
קלים, she's not married. Even
קדשים קלים and certainly קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim, It's all משולחן גבוה,
mishulchan gavo'ah, off of God's table, not yours. You can't marry a
woman with it. רב אמר עדיין היא מחלוקת. Rav amar adayin hi
machlokes. רב Rav said they never took a vote, רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. kept his position, and they're still debating
the issue. There's still a position that it doesn't work.
Okay, Rabbi Yehuda is a troublemaker.
Well, I don't know, troublemaker.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, is it different than in the משנה? Mishnah.
Because the משנה Mishnah, says it depends on whether שוגג או מזיד.
shogeg o meizid.
No, no, not by the קרבנות. korbanos. That was by מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni and by
normal by
הקדש, hekdesh like money of הקדש, hekdesh. not a קרבן. korban That
was a misuse. The end of the משנה. Mishnah? No, but המקדש
בחלקו, hamikadesh bechelko, it doesn't matter.
רבי יהודה אומר בשוגג לא
קידש.
Rabbi Yehuda
omer beshogeg lo kadesh.
Wait, what are you talking about? You're talking about the end of
the משנה, Mishnah, the fourth line of the משנה?
Mishnah Yeah, that's מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni All right. ורב אמר עדיין
היא מחלוקת. v'Rav amar adayin hi machlokes. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye.
Okay.
So he says רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda still held his position that
it worked. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, כוותיה דרבי יוחנן מסתברא. k'vasei d'Rabbi
Yochanan mistabra. It makes sense like Rabbi Yochanan that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda reversed himself and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? agreed that it doesn't
work. דתניא, detanya. we taught a ברייתא. braita And this is going
to be a, just to tell you where we're going with it,
a passage from the ספרא, Sifra, from
תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim on the תנאי Tannaic commentary on ויקרא. Vayikra.
And the author of the ספרא Sifra or the
editor/author is assumed to be רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda So we're going
to quote a ברייתא braita? that's assumed to be under the authorship
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda to prove that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
in the end agreed to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that it was
not the money of the כהן. Kohen.
Did
you refer to פסקאות piskaot in מדרשי הלכה midreshei halacha as ברייתא?
braita, Yes.
When the גמרא Gemara quotes a מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, it says
דתניא. detanya. Anything that's not a משנה, Mishnah תוספתא, Tosefta, ברייתא, braita.
מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, דתניא. Okay, we taught a ברייתא. baraita מניין
שאין חולקין מנחה כנגד זבחים. minayin she'ein cholkin mincha kineged zvachim.
How do you know when it comes time at the end of
the day, you had all these קרבנות korbanos brought and we're dividing
them up amongst the
כהנים? Kohanim, And a מנחה mincha is also קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim.
So how do you know that, you're dividing them up among the
male כהנים, kohanim, you can say, look, I'm a vegetarian. Just give
me the מנחה, mincha, you can have my part of the קרבנות
korbanos or you can get my steaks. I'm like, great, I'll take
the steaks, you take my מנחה. mincha. How do you know you're
not allowed to do that? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, וכל מנחה אשר
תאפה בתנור לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כחיו. v'chol mincha asher teafeh
b'tanur l'chol bnei Aharon tihyeh ish k'achiv. Every מנחה mincha should be
equal to all בני אהרן, bnei Aharon,
which means that you have to divide up each קרבן korban equally
and you don't get to sort of say, I'll swap you this
for this. No. Everybody gets an equal portion of the מנחה, mincha,
and presumably even after you get your portion, you can't go afterwards
and swap it, which is going to be the proof that it's
not your money. You're given your portion, you have to eat it,
you can't trade it for somebody else's portion in something else. Okay,
now. יכול לא יחלקו מנחות כנגד זבחים. yachol lo yachal'ku menachos kineged
zvachim. Maybe you can't trade off מנחה mincha for זבחים, zvachim, שלא
באו תחתיהם בדלות, shelo bau tachtehem bidalus, because a מנחה mincha when
somebody is poor and certain קרבנות korbanos are sliding scale, a מנחה
mincha is never a substitute
for a sheep or a cow. A מנחה mincha would only be
a substitute on the sliding scale קרבן korban. for a bird. אבל
יחלקו מנחות כנגד עופות, aval yachal'ku menachos kineged ofos,
but maybe if we're dividing bird sacrifices and מנחות, menachos, we can
swap them, you can have more birds, I'll take more of the
מנחות, menachos, שהרי באו... sheharei bau... שהרי קמה תחתיהם בטיבי, she'harei kama
tachteihem bitavi, because they're somewhat seen as a substitute for one another.
Because if somebody is poor they bring a bird, and if they're
super poor, they bring a מנחה. Mincha. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, וכל
נעשה במרחשת ולכל בני אהרן תהיה. v'khol na'aseh bamarkhesheth ul'khol benei Aharon
tihyeh.
So you have all these פסוקים pesukim by the מנחות menachos that
say, "This מנחה Mincha goes to all בני אהרן, benei Aharon, this
מנחה Mincha goes to all בני אהרן, benei Aharon, this מנחה Mincha
goes to all בני אהרן." benei Aharon. Like, just tell me once.
So the fact that it keeps on telling you again and again
and again, the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha learns, teaches you that you
don't divide anything, okay? Not just מנחות menachos you don't divide, you
know, you don't divide מנחות menachos against anything else, you don't divide
other קרבנות, korbanos, nothing gets swapped, okay? That's how we're going to
learn it. So the extra פסוק pasuk tells me you don't even
swap a מנחה Mincha for a bird. Okay. יכול לא יחלקו מנחות
כנגד עופות? Yakhol lo yakhluku menachos kineged ofos? Maybe you don't swap
a מנחה Mincha for the bird sacrifices? You know, you don't sort
of trade them off in the division? שהלו מיני דמים והלו מיני
קמחים? she'hallu minei damim v'hallu minei kemakhim? This has blood, it's an
animal, and this is flour. אבל יחלקו עופות כנגד זבחים? Aval yakhluku
ofos kineged zevakhim?
Maybe swap, you know,
the birds for the like the sheep? רש״י Rashi says the reason
he used the word זבחים zevakhim by the like the sheep and
the cows is because they are slaughtered, okay? Whereas the עופות, ofos,
you do the מליקה. melika. Okay, so anyway, שהלו והלו מיני דמים.
she'hallu v'hallu minei damim. It's both two types of blood and meat.
So, so I can swap you, I'll keep the birds, you keep
the meat. I'm trying to keep off red meat. תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, על מחבת. al machavath. No, again, a פסוק pasuk. by the
fire pan offering, that that has to be divided equally. So that
teaches you so it's not about מנחה, Mincha, but it's an extra
פסוק. pasuk So all these extra פסוקים pesukim that say divide equally
tell me that you don't do any swapping, okay? Every single one
tells me you don't do this type of swapping and that type
of swapping. יכול לא יחלקו עופות כנגד זבחים שהלו מעשיהם ביד והלו
מעשיהם בכלי? Yakhol lo yakhluku ofos kineged zevakhim she'hallu ma'aseihem b'yad v'hallu
ma'aseihem bikheli? Maybe you don't do the birds opposite the זבחים zevakhim
because in one you use a vessel, meaning a knife, and the
other you use your hand, the fingernail. אבל יחלקו מנחות כנגד מנחות?
Aval yakhluku menachos kineged menachos? Ah! Maybe like, you I'm trying to
keep off fried food, so you get the fried מנחה Mincha and
I'll get the baked מנחה. Mincha. Okay? Maybe at least that we
could do. Okay. שהלו והלו מעשיהם ביד. she'hallu v'hallu ma'aseihem b'yad. And
they both, you know, use יד yad and they're both קמח kemach
and they're both very similar categories. תלמוד לומר וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן
לכל בני אהרן. Talmud lomar v'khol minkha belulah bashamen l'khol benei Aharon.
Another פסוק pasuk? that you divide it equally. לא יחלקו מחבת כנגד
מרחשת מרחשת כנגד מחבת. Lo yakhluku machavath kineged markhesheth markhesheth kineged machavath.
So maybe you don't do, you know, different types of מנחות menachos
one against the other. You know, so the מרחשת markhesheth is one
where it's like a deep pan, like it's a deep pot. So
it's more and the other, well no, the מחבת machavath is more
the fried, I think the מרחשת markhesheth is the more boiled or
whatever. Anyway, שזו מעשיהם רכים וזו מעשיהם קשים. shezu ma'aseihem rakhim v'zu
ma'aseihem kashim. And the מחבת machavath is hard, it's like a fried
wafer. The מרחשת markhesheth is more like, you know, oily or doughnut
or something like that. Anyway,
אבל יחלקו מחבת כנגד מחבת ומרחשת כנגד מרחשת. Aval yakhluku machavath kineged
machavath u'markhesheth kineged markhesheth. Now that I would think you could do!
I have all the מנחות menachos of one genre. Let's say, okay,
we got twenty מנחות מרחשת menachos markhesheth brought today, we have twenty
כהנים, kohanim. each one take one. No, you can't do that.
What you have to do is you have to take every single
קרבן korban and divide each individual קרבן korban. that was brought by
the כהנים. kohanim Okay, I mean I that's gotta be such a
whatever such a You have all these tiny little pieces. I mean,
that seems really bizarre, right?
By how many כהנים kohanim? are you talking about?
I don't know, see, I don't know exactly what numbers we're talking
about.
Ten כהנים? kohanim, I don't know.
All right, anyway, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, שהלו והלו מעשיהם קשים אי
נמי מעשיהם רכים. she'hallu v'hallu ma'aseihem kashim i nami ma'aseihem rakhim.
So תלמוד לומר וחרבה לכל בני אהרן תהיה. Talmud lomar v'kharevah l'khol
benei Aharon tihyeh. Okay, so again, what's that wind up saying? And
I really that just makes it it's hard to understand conceptually and
logistically. I mean, I guess conceptually you could understand it. You know,
maybe from your perspective, you the כהנים, kohanim. you got all these
מנחות, menachos, you wanted to like divide them in a more efficient
way. But I brought the קרבן. Korban And from my perspective, you
know, that was my קרבן Korban and I want that to be
shared by the כהנים. kohanim. Maybe there's something symbolically significant. So I
guess I could understand that, but logistically it's gotta be a nightmare.
You can't even just combine all of the same genre and divide
it at the end of the day. Each קרבן Korban, has to
be divided equally amongst the כהנים. kohanim. יכול
לא יחלקו בקדשי קדשים? Yakhol lo yakhluku b'kodshei kodashim? Maybe this is
only קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim you know, מנחות menachos and זבחים? zevakhim?
And and אבל יחלקו בקדשים קלים? aval yakhluku b'kodashim kallim? Maybe by
שלמים? That has a lower level and maybe that's more of a
sense of ownership, and maybe there there can be some trade-offs, you
know, and trading that goes on. תלמוד לומר איש כאחיו וסמיך ליה
אם על תודה יקריבנו. Talmud lomar ish k'akhiv v'samikh leih im al
todah yakrivennu. So the end of all those discussions of dividing the
מנחות, menachos, it then transitions to talking about a שלמים, a תודה.
todah. So even by the שלמים, you're not allowed to swap and
subdivide. Just as you don't swap. כשם שאין חולקין בקדשי קדשים כך
אין חולקין בקדשים קלים. Keshem she'ein kholkin b'kodshei kodashim kakh ein kholkin
b'kodashim kallim. Now,
what do we learn out איש כאחיו? ish k'akhiv? איש איש חולק
אפילו בעל מום. ish ish kholke afilu ba'al mum.
Even somebody a כהן kohen who has a מום mum and can't
do the עבודה avodah gets a portion in the קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim That's actually point out that's actually more of a מפורש פסוק
meforash pasuk anyway.
Anyway what you see is you can't do any swapping within a
between קרבנות. korbanot. So obviously you have no right in it if
you can't swap my
my מנחה mincha for
your מנחה mincha then how could I marry a woman with it?
I don't have any sense of ownership over it. סתם ספרא מני
Stam Sifra mani and who is this ספרא Sifra going like an
anonymous ספרא Sifra רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda. It's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda,
והוא קאמר דלית בה דין חלוקה
כלל. vehu ka'amar d'leis bah din chalukah klal. There's no sense of
swapping and trading that can be done with this. So clearly you
don't have any ownership over it. שמע מינה Shma mina you see
that in the end even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree you
cannot marry a woman and even with קדשים קלים because in the
end we included even קדשים קלים in this. חזר בו. Chazar bo.
Yeah which is ממנו וגמרו mimenu ugmoro as the גמרא Gemara. says
before. אמר רבא וכרב מי לא תניא? Amar Rava vechirav mi lo
tanya? What do you mean? You have nothing to support רב'ס Rav's
idea that there would say that you would have a portion in
the קרבנות korbanot and that you maybe could marry a woman? והתניא
Vehatanya ודתנא ברייתא v'detana baraita
הצנועים מושכים את ידיהם. hatznuim moshchin es yadeihem. After the period of
שמעון הצדיק Shimon Hatzadik it says that the it says in the
time of שמעון הצדיק Shimon Hatzadik there was a ברכה bracha in
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and all you had to do was
get like a little bit and you'd be satisfied. After his time
it was not and the bread would not satisfy the כהנים. kohanim
So and everybody only got a little piece of the לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim right? It wasn't like קרבנות korbanot you could have a
lot of קרבנות korbanot in any day but לחם הפנים lechem hapanim
you only have a very small finite amount. So it says the
more modest כהנים kohanim would just withdraw their hands. Like why am
I going to fight other כהנים for a slight little bigger piece
and it's not even going to be so satisfying?
I know but you would think you're just doing it לשם מצוה
leshem mitzvah but it seems that like no you want to actually
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim was eaten once a week on שבת. Shabbos.
Anyway so it says the צנועים tznuim since they weren't going to
be get get a big piece and it wasn't going to be
satisfying or whatever they didn't want to fight they just stood back.
Okay ומושכין ידיהם. umoshchin yadeihem. והגרגרנים Vehagargarnim and the sort of I
don't know ravenous ones חולקין cholkin they would take a part of
it. מאי חולקין? Mai cholkin? Now what does that mean? Does it
just mean they would divide it? No it means חוטפין chotfin it
means they would grab. דתניא סיפא Dekatanya seifa מעשה באחד שחטף חלקו
וחלק חברו. ma'aseh be'echad shechataf chelko vechelek chaveiro. Somebody grabbed his portion
and his friend's
portion so it wasn't enough to have his
portion he wanted was so they
felt it was such a small portion they were grabbing from other
people. והיו קורין אותו בן חמצן עד יום מותו Vehayu korin oso
ben hamtzan ad yom moso and they would call him the sort
of the grabber or the thief until the day of his death.
אמר רבה בר רב שילא מאי קרא? Amar Rabbah bar Rav Shila
mai kra? What's the פסוק? pasuk אלהי פלטני מיד רשע Elohai paltini
miyad rasha that חמצן hamtzan means the same as like a חמצן
hamtzan like a thief פלטני מיד רשע מכף מעול וחומץ paltini miyad
rasha mikaf me'avel vechometz
from the one that sort of trespasses and and robs and seizes.
רבא אמר מהכא Rava amar mehacha למדו היטב דרשו משפט אשרו חמוץ
limdu heiteiv dirshu mishpat ashru chamotz חמוץ chamotz excuse me the one
who is oppressed or the one who now now what does this
have to do with okay right what does it have to do
with our point? So if you look at רש"י Rashi רש"י Rashi
says like this רש"י Rashi says
four lines down in the wide lines near the end of the
lines רש"י Rashi says or we can do the middle the beginning
of that line fourth line down אלא חולקין דרך עילוי מניח חלקו
לחברו ונוטל כנגדו במקום אחר. Ella cholkin derech iluy maniach chelko l'chaveiro
venotel kenegdo bimakom acher. I'm sorry I misread the גמרא. Gemara The
גמרא Gemara says so I'm sorry because I read it all as
the same proof right? It should have been והגרגרנים חולקין. vehagargarnim cholkin.
So when it said the ravenous ones divided it period that was
his proof that you did have a portion because it assumed what
it meant was if we say that we divided it it means
we divided
it amongst ourselves. So we we've elbowed out the more modest ones
we're the ravenous ones and we'll figure out amongst ourselves how to
divide it. So that sounds like we have some rights over it
and we can decide how to trade it off and how to
divide it and that we may now by the way תוספות Tosfos
says even within the position that you are not that you are
not חולקין cholkin א' כנגד ב' A keneged B you can still
divide equally you can still divide within one קרבן. Korban So if
we have like if we've divided a מנחה mincha between us and
you're not so hungry and I would say would you mind giving
me your portion in the מנחה mincha you're entitled to give that
to me. Okay? So that's not really חולקין. cholkin. It's like within
one קרבן Korban, right so it's when you're swapping it for something
else for really
swapping it for something else.
So that's basically what the גמרא Gemara thought. The גמרא Gemara, thought
הגרגרנים חולקין hagargarnim cholkin the ravenous ones would divide it meaning we're
going to take it amongst ourselves and you'll give it to me
and I'll give you something else for it and whatever. And therefore
it would seem to be like you did have a right to
swap for your portion in the קרבן. Korban. And the answer was
no מאי חולקין חוטפין. mai cholkin chotfin. חולקין Cholkin does not mean
swap it for something else it means you you just grab. It
would be like at a קידוש kiddush okay? Right? רש"י Rashi yeah
and everybody would be grabbing it. And as תוספות Tosfos says either
it means I stole from you but be also we're subdividing within
one thing we're not
swapping. And since we're not swapping it for something else, we're just
subdividing within one thing, this is not a proof that it is
then it does not indicate that it's your ממון. mammon. Yes.
Is this story just a קשיא kasha on נמרו וגמרו? Nimru ve-Gamru?
Yes. Okay, meaning the point is, so just to summarize what we
said, meaning the argument was does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the
end back down and say you don't have a portion in קרבנות
Korbanot and you can't marry a woman with it? So the evidence
was was that he did back down because he's the author of
the ספרא Sifra and he basically says that you can't swap meaning
within one קרבן Korban each individual's קרבן Korban. you can subdivide it
and maybe do some swapping, you know, some I guess giving away
or, you know, assigning portions but that's within each individual's קרבן, but
you can't swap any portion in any קרבן for any other קרבן,
so clearly you have no real rights to it, no real ownership
over it and you can't marry a woman even according to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda That was the basic point. The answer was wait,
but we have this ברייתא that says by לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim
they would swap, they would חוטפים, chotfim, which seems to be they
would swap and it seems to be that that would be an
idea that you do have rights and the answer is no, they
wouldn't swap it for other things, they would just grab bigger portions
within the same קרבן. And but but the idea that you could
swap, but nobody says at the end of the day you could
swap your portion in a קרבן for something other for something else,
okay, you could do any real trading with a קרבן. And therefore
even רבי יהודה, nobody in the end says you can marry a
woman with the portion in קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and even we're
saying with קדשים קלים as well. Meaning it might be...
yes Charlie? The ספרא Sifra would have been
written before the משנה Mishnah. was compiled?
There's a whole question, you know I mean that's what what's his
name deals with, הלבני Halivni deals with in מדרש ומשנה. Midrash u-Mishnah.
I mean sometimes sometimes, you know, everything has like late editings, so
sometimes it sounds like the משנה's Mishnah quoting a passage from the
מדרש הלכה, Midrash Halacha, sometimes the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha says, you
know, you know I forget what the language is but it quotes
a line that's a line from a משנה. Mishna So you know
there anyway they were being done in parallel times, there's always a
whole question like was forget when the actual text was edited, the
really the more interesting question is which approach was primary? Did we
start with like looking at פסוקים, pesukim, not knowing the הלכה, Halakha,
deriving using using the process of מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha and then
after we did a whole process of derivation we distilled and organized
the conclusions as the משנה Mishna as the הלכות Halachot in the
משניות Mishnayot or did we start with traditions of practice and then
go back and look at the פסוקים pesukim and try to derive
and infer? That's the more interesting question than the question of exactly
when this text was edited because they were like edited over a
period of time and in parallel and so on. So that question
there's a real debate among scholars. Again I don't know sadly or
not sadly the most
the best answer is both is that it wasn't that there was
a clear sequence like there were traditions, there were דרשות, drashot, they
were sort of both happening at the same time. Yes Charlie you
have...
yeah a follow up to this, there are lots of שיעורים shiurim
on משניות Mishnayot and we regularly study... I've never seen anybody study...
Okay well we
can you can you can fund one and we'll have it here
in the שול, shul, yes.
Excuse me in the end saying that it was sort of understood
maybe לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim some people would refrain and maybe those
that didn't get and the other people got more would give them
something
else?
What? No no no, it's sort of like in a קידוש Kiddush
like I'm not going to go ahead and fight everybody in the
קידוש, Kiddush, forget it I'll go I'll go eat it home and
other people are like, you know, trying to get their portion. That's
what the scene it's describing. But all it's saying is that the
word חוטפים chotfim does not mean I'm swapping my piece of לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim for your portion in something else. I'm just grabbing
a smaller or a bigger portion and therefore it's no proof that
there's any sense of ownership over the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. Yes.
Since they ate the חמץ chametz and they likely took...
yeah yeah but I don't want to go there. Okay that's interesting
חמץ chametz and חומץ chometz I didn't think about that. Right interesting.
Okay well you're talking about also vinegar. Let's move on.
Basically it becomes one big קידוש.
Kiddush. Right exactly. Moving on. Well we have to have a wedding
hall so here's the קידוש Kiddush after... here's the שמורג. smorg. We
got the שמורג smorg in the wedding hall. Okay now moving
on. מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni. God. מעשר שני, maaser sheni okay,
alright anyway alright. מעשר שני בין בשוגג בין במזיד לא קידש דברי
רבי מאיר. Ma'aser Sheni bein beshogeg bein bemezid lo kadesh divrei Rabbi
Meir. מעשר שני maaser sheni doesn't work intentionally or knowingly or
unknowingly. רבי יהודה אומר שוגג לא קידש מזיד קידש, Rabbi Yehuda omer
shogeg lo kadesh mezid kadesh, unintentionally no,
intentionally yes. So although רבי יהודה seems a little more interesting what's
the difference between שוגג shogeg and מזיד mezed, we're going to really
focus on רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir at least initially. מנא הני מילי?
Mina hani mili? Where does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. get this idea
that you can't use מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money? Meaning by קרבנות
Korbanos we spoke about this idea of משולחן גבוה קא זכו. mishulchan
gavoah ka zachu. Where does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir get this idea
that you can't use מעשר שני Maaser Sheni, money that that's not
yours? You're going to bring it up to ירושלים Yerushalayim, and money
even the fruit you're going to bring it up to ירושלים, Yerushalayim.
eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Why should it not be considered
yours? So אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא משמיה דגמרא, Amar Rav Acha
brei d'Rava mishmei d'Gemara, so it says in the name of Rava
in the name of the גמרא, Gemara which is interesting, the name
of like the traditions that were accepted in the בית מדרש. Beis
Medrash. וכל מעשר הארץ מזרע הארץ מפרי העץ להשם הוא, V'chol maaser
ha-aretz mi-zera ha-aretz mi-pri ha-etz la-Hashem hu, all the מעשר maaser goes
to God since it's talking about מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni קדש להשם,
Kodesh la-Hashem,
holy to God. So the combination of those two words, holy to
God,
means it is like not yours. It's another way of saying שלחן
גבוה. shulchan gavoha. You're eating it, but you are eating something that
is holy to God, that is not yours. You're eating
God's
produce. Okay. I knew that was coming. Okay. להשם הוא. La-Hashem hu.
Okay. להשם הוא ולא לקדש
בו אשה. La-Hashem hu v'lo l'kadesh bo isha.
It's God's, it belongs to God, so and not for you to
marry a woman. It's not your ממון. mamon. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, הרי תרומת מעשר דכתיב כן תרימו גם אתם תרומת
השם. Harei trumas maaser d'chsiv kein tarimu gam atem trumas Hashem. You
should take the תרומה truma of God. ותנן, U'tnan, so it's called
God's. ותנן המקדש בתרומה מקודשת. U'tnan ha-mekadesh bi-truma mekudeshes.
If a man marries a woman, a כהן kohen with his תרומה,
truma, she is married. That is considered his property. גמרא Gemara says
no. דלא כתיב ביה להשם. D'lo ksiv bei la-Hashem. That
says תרומת השם. trumas Hashem.
It's God's תרומה truma because God told you to take it. But
it's not תרומה truma given to God. It's given to the כהן,
kohen, okay? So it still is yours. So the השם Hashem there
means it's commanded by God but not that it belongs to God.
Okay. ודכתיב ביה להשם. V'dichsiv bei la-Hashem. הרי חלה הבחלה דכתיב ביה
תתנו להשם, Harei challa ha-bachala d'chsiv bei titnu la-Hashem,
give it to God. ותנן המקדש בתרומה מקודשת U'tnan ha-mekadesh bi-truma mekudeshes
and if you marry a woman with any תרומה, truma, and חלה
challa is considered a type of תרומה, truma, she's married. So דלא
כתיב ביה קדש. D'lo ksiv bei kodesh. Yes, that says it's God's
but it doesn't say holy to God. If it's holy and belongs
to God, then it's completely not yours, completely off limits. קדש Kodesh
and להשם. la-Hashem. הרי שביעית דכתיב בה יובל היא קדש תהיה לכם.
Harei shevi'is d'chsiv ba yovel hi kodesh tihye lachem. ותנן המקדש בפירות
שביעית מקודשת. U'tnan ha-mekadesh b'peiros shevi'is mekudeshes.
Now by the way רש״י Rashi points out that the משנה Mishna.
never says המקדש בפירות שביעית מקודשת, ha-mekadesh b'peiros shevi'is mekudeshes, but the
previous משנה spoke about the guy who married the five women with
the figs of שמיטה shemita and it said that they were married,
so that's implicitly saying that. So the גמרא Gemara says no. דלא
כתיב ביה להשם. D'lo ksiv bei la-Hashem. That's קדש תהיה לכם. kodesh
tihye lachem.
So I don't know, we just want to go through everything. הרי
תרומה דכתיב
קדש ישראל להשם, Harei truma d'chsiv kodesh Yisrael la-Hashem, Israel is holy
to God. ראשית תבואתה. Reishis tevuaso. So you
know Israel is like תרומה, truma, they're the first of the offering
of God's crop. So you know sort of the analogy of you
know like the first of the crop, the first of the nations.
Anyway, where's the תרומה? truma? So we're being analogized there to תרומה
truma and we're called קדש להשם. kodesh la-Hashem. ותנן המקדש בתרומה מקודשת.
U'tnan ha-mekadesh bi-truma mekudeshes. גמרא Gemara says no, אהישראל כתיב. a-Yisrael ksiv.
That's not talking about real תרומה, truma, that's talking about the Jewish
people. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, but it's using a
metaphor. ולאו ממילא שמעת מינה? V'lav mi-meila shamas mina?
Fine, it's using a metaphor but the metaphor is תרומה. truma. And
the metaphor is קדש להשם, kodesh la-Hashem, so implicitly it's saying that
תרומה truma is קדש להשם. kodesh la-Hashem. So the גמרא Gemara says
תרגמה רבין סבא קמיה דרב אמר קרא הוא בהוא יתיה. Targuma Ravin
Sava kammai d'Rav amar kra hu b'hu yese. You
know what? You're right. By תרומה truma you do have a פסוק
pasuk that says קדש להשם, kodesh la-Hashem, but it also that פסוק
pasuk? also says הוא. hu. What's the פסוק? מעשר
להשם
הוא. Maaser la-Hashem hu. Okay, so oh sorry no, actually not by
תרומה. truma. It's not enough that by מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni it
says קדש להשם. kodesh la-Hashem. קדש להשם Kodesh la-Hashem would not totally
make it off limits, but it also says הוא. hu. It says
להשם הוא, la-Hashem hu, which means it remains God's, in no way
does it move away from that state of being God's. Okay. So
by מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni we have קדש להשם הוא kodesh la-Hashem
hu and the combination of all those three means that it's totally
not yours according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir So this is רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. So we've already established that קדשי קדשים and
קדשים קלים, even according to רבי יוסי הגלילי who says קדשים קלים
ממון בעלים, but when the time comes to eat the meat of
קדשי קדשים and קדשים קלים, משלחן גבוה קזכו, mishulchan gavoha kazchu, it's
not your meat, you're eating off of God's table. And now we're
saying that מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is also what the גמרא Gemara calls ממון גבוה הוא. mamon gavoha
hu. Okay, not משלחן גבוה קזכו, mishulchan gavoha kazchu, it uses a
different phrase ממון גבוה הוא mamon gavoha hu and therefore completely not
yours, you're eating God's מעשר ma'aser and therefore you cannot use it
to do קידושין kiddushin with.
So what we're trying to understand is if I tried, is it
מעילה me'ilah. or is it not effective?
It's just well we're going to get to that very soon by
קדשים. But here, so there's no מעילה by מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni,
but what you're asking is exactly getting to the final part of
the משנה. Okay. Now we have not identified why according to רבי
יהודה it works by שוגג shogeg and not by מזיד mezed. wait,
it works by מזיד mezed. and not by שוגג, shogeg right? Yeah,
it works by מזיד mezed and not by שוגג. shogeg So I'll
just tell you the answer, we're going to read it in the
גמרא Gemara but let me just because the גמרא's going to sort
of shift a little and then circle back. So the basic point
is like this: רבי יהודה fundamentally disagrees. He says מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni, is not ממון גבוה, mamon gevoh, it's yours. So if it's
yours, why should you not why should it matter שוגג shogeg or
מזיד? mezed So the simple answer is, it's not your שוגג shogeg
or מזיד, it's the woman's שוגג shogeg or מזיד. If you say
to the woman הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li with
this apple, and she thinks it's a normal apple, and it turns
out it's a מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni, apple, what's she going to
do if she wants to eat the apple?
She's going to eat it now?
No, what what she if it's a מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni apple,
what does she have to do with it?
She has
to bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So she says, excuse me? I
never agreed for an apple that I would have to bring up
to ירושלים. Yerushalayim, What good is this to me? So she was
basically duped. She thought it was like a very different type of
an apple than it was. It was one that's absolutely no good
here. So therefore, if she is unwitting and doesn't realize it's מעשר
שני, Ma'aser Sheni אינה מקודשת, eina mekudeshet, because she never agreed to
that type of an apple. If she knows it's מעשר שני, Ma'aser
Sheni and she knows she'll have to bring it, okay, but that's
the אומדנא umdena that we make. If she knows she has to
bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim. then she is מקודשת. That was רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda. So let's take a look now. Okay, and then
we're going to get into a similar issue by
קודש. kodesh. Okay, ובהקדש במזיד קידש בשוגג לא קידש דברי רבי מאיר.
uvhekedsh bemezed kidesh beshogeg lo kidesh divrei Rabbi Meir. By הקדש, hekdesh
if it's intentional it works, if you know what you're doing it
works, if not it doesn't. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
רבי יהודה אומר בשוגג קידש במזיד לא קידש, Rabbi Yehuda omer beshogeg
kidesh bemezed lo kidesh, the reverse. So we're going to bracket the
last רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. We're going to focus on the fact
that by מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
it works במזיד, and by הקדש, hekdesh רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it works by מזיד. Why is מזיד better than שוגג shogeg in
those two cases? So let's take a look. אמר רבי יעקב, Amar
Rabbi Yaakov, רב יעקב Rav Yaakov said, שמעת מינה דרבי יוחנן תרתי,
shemat mina deRabbi Yochanan tarti, I heard from רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
two things. שיגת מעשר דרבי יהודה, shigat ma'aser deRabbi Yehuda, he explained
why by מעשר Ma'aser, according to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda שוגג shogeg
doesn't work, ושיגת הקדש דרבי מאיר, veshigat hekdesh deRabbi Meir, and why
by הקדש hekdesh. by רבי מאיר שוגג doesn't work and מזיד does.
שניהם, shneihem, and in both of those cases we say, אין אשה
מתקדשת בהם. ein isha mitkadeshet bahem. Okay, a woman is not married.
Now חדא, chada, in one of those cases the reason it doesn't
work בשוגג beshogeg is לפי שאין אשה רוצה, lefi she'ein isha rotza,
the woman would not have agreed to it had she known. וחדא,
vechada, in one of those cases לפי ששניהם רוצים, lefi sheshneihem rotzim,
neither of them would have agreed to it had they known. Now
by the way Michael, in terms of your question of אומדנא, umdena,
רש"י Rashi says the נפקא מינה nafka mina is if we know
who we're presuming to have the problem with, we can always then
ask that person and determine oh you didn't mind, it's okay. So
do we assume that one of them didn't want to or neither
of them wanted to? So let's explain it. It's tough sometimes anyway.
Right. ולא ידענא הי מינייהו, velo yadana hai minaihu, I don't know
which one of those when it's בשוגג doesn't work it's because one
of them wouldn't have wanted it and which one neither of them
would have wanted it. So we'll just read one answer now and
we'll continue tomorrow. אמר רב יימר, Amar Rav Yeimar, נחזי אנן, nechezi
anan, fine, גוט, gut, that's a nice little puzzle, let's figure that
out ourselves. מעשר, ma'aser, by מעשר, ma'aser, איהי לא ניחא לה, eehee
lo nicha lah, she doesn't want מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni had she
known she would not have said yes, okay, and that's why it
doesn't work if it's unaware, משום טירחא דאורחא, mishum tircha de'orcha, she
has to schlep it up to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But he, איהו ניחא
ליה, eehoo nicha leh, why would he have a problem? I know
it's מעשר, she's willing to take my מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni fruit,
all the better way, all the better, דמתפרקא מיניה, demitparka minei, now
I don't have to bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim So if they're
both ignorant from... he has no problem using מעשר שני fruit, but
she would be the one who wouldn't be happy with it had
she known and that's why it doesn't work. אלא הקדש, Ela hekdesh,
but if it's הקדש, תרווייהו לא ניחא להו, traveihu lo nicha lehu,
neither of them would have wanted הקדש had they realized it was
הקדש. Why not? לא ניחא להו דניפוק הקדש לחולין על ידיהו, lo
nicha lehu denafik hekdesh lechulin al yadeihu, because when you give הקדש
and it's not yours to give, you're being עובר over on the
איסור מעילה, issur me'ilah, you're transgressing, you're being מוציא הקדש לחולין. motzi
hekdesh lechulin. So neither of them would have wanted to have been
party to this forbidden transaction. So שוגג doesn't... so שוגג doesn't work
by מעשר שני according to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda because even though
מעשר שני is your money, we presume she would not have wanted
to take it had she known, and הקדש doesn't work according to
רבי מאיר because if it's בשוגג we presume neither of them would
have wanted to do it because neither of them would have wanted
to have been party to an act of מעילה. Okay, we'll continue
with this tomorrow to see other ways of understanding why שוגג would
not work in the case of מעשר שני and the case of
הקדש.
Not פדיון pidyon it's לשון חילול, lashon chillul,
חילול הקדש, chillul hekdesh, right. Okay, we have to get out of
here because Seth's starting a class starting exactly now.
So what's the point of that last opinion, what would be the
problem with using מעשר שני in ירושלים Yerushalayim. to...? What? Not a
problem,
I mean go to ירושלים.
That might not be a problem.